all right so we left last time having
just made this thing with curly brackets
that goes from like right here down
right and it's got a name here and I
kind of you know stumbled with what I
called it because depending on who you
talk to and when they were born they'll
tell you a different word for what that
thing is let's talk about that what is
it okay so in my world I told you it's a
sub routine and the reason I pick the
word sub routine which you'll never find
any other YouTuber using that term but
the reason I like sub routine is because
that generalized
term specifically speaks to a bunch of
instructions grouped
together a sub routine is a bunch of
instructions grouped together now what
those instructions
do is what distinguishes the next three
terms that I'm about to use okay the
next three terms that I'm about to use
is is what we're going to cover with
this okay there are
procedures there are
functions and well and there are methods
but methods are the implementations of
operations so let's say
four okay and
honestly those are four terms that you
should memorize and a lot of people on
the internet and on YouTube and places
like that they're going to tell you this
code routines are not not a thing okay
no a Cod routine is a
function that runs in a separate thread
we'll get there so these are the terms I
want you to memorize put those in your
notes okay you already started your
notes we talked about how to do that the
terms to memorize are sub rutine so the
sub routine is the generalized term um
and as a point of reference Pearl uses
sub to Define everything okay um
and then you have the
specific things you have and and every
every you know operations don't
necessarily but a method definitely does
so you have all these things generally
have a block well what is a block make
sure your block block goes into your
terminology okay make sure a block goes
into your terminology the inside of the
block right the body is inside of the
block the and then you know the the
block is anything between curly brackets
in bash in Python it's everything
indented to the same level and C it's
everything within cly brackets in
JavaScript it's everything between cly
brackets the biggest distinction between
Python and C like languages they're
called is the use of curly brackets for
a block and there are a lot of really
distinct advantages to doing that python
is permanently hobbled in fact if you
want to get a really you want to get a
good lap go read the thread where the
python team tried to create first class
functions with multiple lines and r into
the problem of significant Whit space
completely hobbling them and they all
just kind of went their separate ways
and ignored it because it's stopped it
stopped it in its
tracks um so we're g to we'll get that
so so here's here's here's what we need
to say uh about this um why is
everything you're saying um we're not
going to we're not going to talk about
that no we're not we're not going to
talk about that because we're not
talking about python at all we're
talking about bash people are suggesting
things okay so here's here's the thing
you know what a block is and you know
what a sub routine is a sub routine if
you want to get
really Limited in this a sub routine is
a named block
okay and and let's just leave it at that
okay so so in a strictest sense what
we're looking at right now right here
whoops right right here how am I doing
this how am I doing this how about that
while we're looking at these things
right here these These are named blocks
they're otherwise called you can call
them sub rtin but that's not what
they're called in bash so somebody is
going to come unglued because you're
going to nuh you're you're talking about
functions
right uh so they're they're saying
you're talking about functions those are
all functions and I I'm going to tell
you they are not functions I don't care
what bash calls them they are not
functions because look up the definition
of a function and you'll see so let's
start with what these actually are and
this is one of the things I like about
Pascal Pascal is an old Boomer language
that was used to teach people to code
and everything and it separated out
there was a separate keyword for
procedure and a separate keyword for
function because they're different and
I'm going to tell you the difference and
you're going to know the difference and
99% of the people on YouTube have no
I sorry I swore about the
difference I feel strongly about this
because if you know the difference
you'll write better code because mixing
the two into one block is a bad idea
always has been right I'm getting
emotional because I care about this
stuff so just so you know the difference
here's what it is a
procedure a procedure as I said is just
a bunch of instructions that can have
side
effects so let me let me ask you a
question do these things have side
effects what are their side
effects a side effect is something that
affects the
environment in which the thing
runs right it it's not it doesn't do
things that are contained that's what a
function is which we'll get to it does
things that have side effects it does
things that affect its environment and I
I already ranted about this before but
I'm doing it again I don't care I can't
say it enough so in this case we have a
global variable right so this variable
is visible both to this procedure and to
this
procedure right so we have the greeting
is
contained in here in fact if we wanted
to we could actually uh you see how
echo's greeting there we could actually
declare greeting to be local and not
have a
problem okay now it's local right now it
can't be used outside of this block
outside of this procedure that is a
procedure okay and but name is a global
and so by the definition strictly
speaking the definition of a function
this is not a function a strictly and in
in in 2024 you have to say things like
true function in order for people to
know what you're talking about let me
let me we're going to get to function
next but let's finish procedure so this
I consider this a procedure because it
is has side effects it's doing things to
things that are not contained within
itself right that's not the only
criteria Pro function but it's one very
very very important one and side effects
are almost always a bad idea if you can
avoid it because why they're harder to
test um uh they're you know they're
super hard to test and you know it's
because there's not just one thing does
you know you put stuff in you get Stu
out we talked about this before but I'm
talking back all right so the next thing
is function so what is a function a
function just returns something so let's
actually write one
right let's write a function let's say
let's let's create a function that takes
uh that just returns something all right
and you know it could be anything I mean
the simplest of functions could just be
um let's actually say random color how
about that uh Rand color and we're going
to repeat uh we're going to make a
random color here and we're going to
this is not going to have any side
effect so we're going to put uh term
color which you can just copy these
these values my friends you can just
copy the values and reuse them in your
own um we haven't talked about variables
and how these are escapes yet just know
that they are a thing uh and these since
this is mad at me because I'm not using
all of these first of all let's declare
all of these as local so I'm going to
put uh CMT local I should probably call
that prefix instead uh local and we're
going to put locals in front of all
that and um we'll go ahead and save that
now they're not being used so you know
that's why it's doing that um I'm
actually this is a shell check thing uh
I'm actually going to turn off the sc20
34 for this block by doing that I'm
going to do a
disable uh shell
check
disable was it
two
um uh expected equals right disable
equals
23074 is that
it oh two two SC 2034
sc20 I think that's it yeah okay does
that only do it for that one I wanted to
do it for the whole block I don't know
how to do it for the whole block I
wonder if we can do it how do I
disable shell check for whole
block there's a way to do it I can't
remember
yeah yeah yes yes yes yes
um disabling
blocks shall check disable equals all
code
block to disable checks for a block wrap
the block with the of code with enable
and
disable
what any code in this block will have
blow oh I guess I have to put it above
it oh that did
it I didn't realize that was it I did I
was doing it wrong before when it's like
this it's only the next line when it's
like this is the whole
block yeah I yeah I guess we have to do
a disable and then an enable again
right uh because it's going to kill it
wait is it going to no I think it's
probably going to be fine here let's try
all right uh term
[Music]
color oh look it's still doing
it it's like it's still doing it okay so
what what that says is it's just the
next it's just the next block in this
case the the block is the next one so
yeah that's good to know okay so that's
good I I now you know so if you if you
want if you want it to shut up then you
know you can do that now obviously I'm
not going to need this um but kind of
want it right so um how are we going to
do this right um so we need to return
one of these colors
um and we don't know about Randomness
yet so let's just go ahead
and return one of the colors
um we don't know about list yet I'm kind
of getting ahead of
myself yeah all right it's time to learn
about lists
all right let's learn about lists my
friends let's say let's do this we's say
colors equals right and and we're going
to put brackets around
it I mean we'll we'll leave this here
but let's actually make this a list and
this this will get rid of our Shield
check problem too um all right so we're
putting you see how it has parenthesis
so you just learned a new thing it's
called a list it's actually called an
array uh
but in Python it's called a list either
way it's a bunch of things sometime it's
called a vector it's like it's a bunch
of things that that are index zero
through whatever unless you're Lua which
starts at one or Ada um so or computer
science it AP Computer Science so anyway
um so colors appears unused so this says
colors is not a thing we can get rid of
all these things now uh uh
CMT yeah I'm going to do that so we got
rid of those those comments in there um
and let's go ahead and save that let's
let's do this though let's say local uh
no we have to declare this right because
this is
big so declare and we're going to make
it a global it has to be declared up
front um why are you putting an r in
front of all your
stuff is that just a thing that happens
on
accident all right so um anyway
this uh so so we have a bunch of colors
here um we actually don't have to do
that though we can put all the colors
inside of our function let's do that if
we put them all in our color and then
nothing else outside of the function
knows about them and that's fine we only
need an array of the colors in here and
you can use declare but when as soon as
you go inside of here in bash you want
to say local they have exactly the same
arguments um so it's called a list it's
it's called a list or an array yes all
right so in bash it's specifically
called an array and um that'll come into
the If You by putting the brackets here
it that the I'm sorry the parentheses it
that makes it automatically a an
array uh the list is zero based yes in
in bash it is so um if you wanted to
though you can get explicit with it and
say you can actually get pass to
local uh you can pass to local an uh an
option to tell it exactly what kind of
type it is um and you see here it tells
you they're the same as declare so if
you do declare it'll you can see here um
okay so this makes names indexed arrays
variables if supported and associ arrays
which will come back those are maps uh
have integer attributes okay so these
are the different types so we we already
know one type right the type is string
and we're going to get to numbers and
stuff later but for right now we're just
going to stick with what we got so if
you wanted to you could do this you
could say a and that says okay this is a
list but you don't need this in in bash
it's just assumed because you have par
uh parenthesis so um now we could
actually do this um this is a part where
traditional show people usually come
unglued we are actually going to print
something we're just going to print
something so we're going to print out
one of the Colors Let's print out red
all right and we're just going to spit
it out we don't care uh one of the great
things about Echo and so let's actually
do this let's turn our other functions
off okay let's turn these off by putting
you know comments in front and now let's
run Rand Lo Rand
color all right and let's just see what
happens actually let's uh let's start
Auto running I have ENT it up here
somewhere did you see what I just did I
want you to see what I just did so
yesterday I used the ENT command and
it's still in my command history so I
was able to use VI mode to use the vi
Search Command slash to find in my
history the command that contained ENT
without any customization of my shell
using standard bash shell this also
works with pic shell so uh you know so
and the way I did that is I I went into
VI mode so um Escape in that case
control F bracket never control C and
you can't with control C it's the main
reason using control C is stupid so if
you you searching here I'm going up and
down with j and k and now I'm going to
find the ENT line because I don't want
to type that again who does I'm going to
type
slent and it's going to come up now
somebody's going to say ell does it
automatically yeah but not on every
system bash and shell do this on every
system with
set-i so we just searched history that's
what we just did we just searched
history let me do that I'm going to do
the sequence again for you okay so first
of all this doesn't work unless you have
set Das oi First Command I execute on
any system I've ever on any system
because the default is not VI it's it's
Emax mode so all these Vim users are
using emac mode for their history how
can you call yourself a Vim user and not
have set-i I mean seriously okay so set
dasi and so now you have Bim search
history now you're when you push k for
up whoops when you escape and then you
push k for up and J for down in my case
Escape was controlled up bracket it
could be Escape you cannot remap
JK you can't remap JK so the people who
burn JK into their
memory and they remap you know caps lock
to escape you can't use VI mode from the
history or VI mode in t-mo or VI mode in
WeChat or VI mode than anything else
because why because you have done
something that only works in
Vim okay so I'm going to make a whole
big thing about this when we're doing
the vi thing but you people who are
doing all of this fancy remapping
instead of using control left bracket
are permanently scarring your muscle
memory in a way that's going to prevent
you from using vim and everything else
besides vim and it just it's completely
irresponsible to tell people to use
control C instead of Escape
completely
irresponsible uh so anyway you cannot
remap so when you when you tell a just
Mar map JK yeah okay and throw out every
other Vim mapping in any application
you're ever going to use use control the
bracket friends okay I'm done I get
really emotional about that because they
don't even know how much they've screwed
themselves over now you know okay so I'm
searching through the history using bi
mode and then I do slash I SL SL
and then I'm going to go ENT you watch
because of the Rants and now I just
found
ENT right I don't even care where it is
I don't care this is called search
centricity is what I call I think I
coined the term search centricity I
don't care about a line number it's on I
just search for it and I find it and I
use it right so I I use it it's exactly
the same command that I used yesterday I
didn't have to retype it I didn't have
to remember it this is also the reason I
do all my command line SE in through the
web from the command line because the
command line history becomes my search
history including my AI
queries okay here we go so so what do I
got here I have a system that's running
greet uh I don't think we're in the
right place for it are we maybe not okay
so there was no change apparently all
right so what are we watching right now
we're watching um uh we're watching
something that is waiting for me to make
a change it's actually running the
program
uh there's just nothing
happening okay
so uh it's ech yeah okay so it's it's
echoing it's echoing random color and um
and then what then we can say Echo uh
something whop something and it will
actually make it red all right so so you
see how it said something but it didn't
make it
red I wonder why oh because we don't
because it's not all right this is
something with Echo versus print up
print up actually does the right thing
um yeah except for see you can either do
Echo e which is not supported
everywhere uh right as reference but not
assigned
oh whoops what am I
doing I do not know what I'm
doing all right there we go red is
reference but not a
sign oh I'm so sorry I am so sorry um
I'm
sorry what what color is red okay so
this is I I'm lost my mind today I got
kind of discombobulated let's do red is
number two no 01
01 all right so there we go wait what
did I get oh that wait wait wait wait
wait
wait I thought it was zerob
based if I got this wrong
we're going to use print up sh'll CH
yells at me because you're never
supposed to put variables inside a print
up according to sh shell Che so we're
going to do this version
instead it's gonna this is going to help
us out though
so uh wait wait we got to put braces
here of course derp derp derp derp derp
all right there we go so
um okay so that was Green Let's do one
is one red one's red okay good okay so
red equals
something uh we are going to make that
we are going to make a list ofat values
that's what we're going to do so so
slowly but surely you guys remember
these other things right but we don't
need the name in front of it now but
what I wanted to show you is that it's
actually printing it
out and so now what we're going to do is
these values let's talk about what they
are first of all let's get rid of these
other
parts okay um and we can we this has got
we are going to do an associative if
you're if you're there's a lot of
backseat drivers right now that are like
do this and do this and this and they're
not doing it progressively so I'm just
kind of helping you out here
so right this one we don't want in there
because that's a reset right we don't
want reset in there these are all colors
okay so these are all the colors all the
colors are loaded in here let's um after
this we're going to talk about
color um but we're not quite ready to
talk about color uh actually let's do
this one let's make this one a a Glo a
global
declare uh we'll say that's a reset okay
so this is a global and we'll have
Global be reset so and that way you can
um you know you can Echo a random color
and then Echo uh well not Rand let's do
print up let's do
print you can either do Echo Das Escape
which I don't like to because it's not
supported
everywhere um but that'll reset your
color right so if you say something else
Echo uh else
something all right oopsie I'm going too
fast okay so you see how it's it's got a
blank kind you see how it also did a
thing here this is why print is usually
better right the problem with print up
is it's going to it's going to like yell
at us right and you don't need multiple
print UPS right I'm doing it the hard
way so you can see uh it's like no you
can't do that you can't do print up here
it's like don't put the reset in there
all right let me show you a better way
to do that so you can do this you can
say I want this to be the
beginning so s right and then we want uh
I think actually I think you can do it
without the brackets if it's if it's a
thing like this I think you can so let's
do uh now wouldn't it be great if we
could have Rand color be a thing you
don't know how to do that yet though
so um let me let me just help with one
other thing so red is
31 and let's put red
here red and then
reset I shell check makes us put that
stuff in there which is kind of stupid
because you really don't need
it you don't so all right not an
identifier I 42 yeah I was afraid of
this yeah so we need to do that umal a
character uh develop for my character
what have I got in
there please tell me
can get away with this WR as reference
but not assigned oh whoopsie I had it
right in the first place
okay so let's go down
here Val red is not an
identifier there okay it's doing it
now yeah let's reset it clear it wait
are we not clearing the screen every
time we are what the hell
declare what do I have I have a problem
line
42 oh
derp such a derpo a
derpo all right that'll work now we can
do this we can say something else and
it'll be white okay all right you see
all right so I mean I'm kind of getting
there the hard way but so but would be
great if we could have it be random so
how do we randomize the color well you
can see the numbers here are between 31
2 3 4 5 6 7even right wouldn't it be
great if we could have a
number that was between
those right so there's a lot of ways to
do this but probably the E so let's talk
about this so we talked about variables
strings variables uh there is a math
random yes but it's not math random
um so what is the back slash I I need to
talk about this for a second okay what
time how long much time we got okay we
got a half an hour so the first thing to
understand here is that this is a real
relatively special type of variable that
only exists in bash this is not a shell
possibility and it's really important
you understand what this does what this
does is it puts the actual
binary into that it doesn't escape it it
it doesn't Escape it but but the result
is an actual binary it's not an escape
of the binary and that is a significant
difference from Shell if you know what
it is all you need to do if you're just
starting out is know that there is a
very
special uh binary sequence and we'll get
into asy later when we do when we do
some some cool things um uh let's see uh
I can do a control left bracket and it
just puts out I don't
know control uh works on mine I don't
I'm American keyboard maybe that's the
reason so um and I mean that's what I
keep typing so here we
have you know back slash e this stands
for an escape and that's that literally
sends the same thing you send to your
screen every time you do an escape when
you're doing a Bim it sends that
specific sequence and that escape tells
the terminal hey get ready here comes
some special information and that
special information begins with a
bracket a square bracket and ends with
the letter M it's a very much a this is
very much a posix terminal thing but any
modern terminal has support for this
okay if your terminal doesn't have
support for this you using an ancient
terminal like pre1
19801 terminal so this escape sequence
then sends it's not it's not um like a
word or something like a string this is
an instruction that changes something
about your terminal the state of your
terminal it tells it okay we are now
everything that happens from now on is
going to be done with the color
red and then it keeps going until it
gets to something else and then if it
gets to another escap an escape they're
called an ANSI if it gets to another as
NC Escape then that changes it based on
what that control sequence is and this
is a really great Rabbit Hole to go down
and and if you want to stay tuned with
this we're going to be doing Bon stuff
and we're going to learn something
called um an or I mean there's chra
that's made a lot of really amazing
things that help you understand
everything that's going on with your
color Terminals and stuff and who
doesn't want color terminal stuff so you
know we go ahead and throw it in here
right now makes it much more fun to
write code doing this so uh you guys
already saw what each of these is um so
this first one is black uh I think I can
pull this off I don't know if I can do
this we're going to find out uh does
that still work sometimes the comments
like that will break it though right uh
the terminal prompts yes you can you can
type ANC codes by hand on your on your
BBS oh my gosh that's really cool um I
don't remember the term colors again so
I have to go look them up I have a
program called term colors which we will
write uh together later but I'm doing it
just to remember which is the order so
we have black red and we'll get into a
whole bunch of things like should you
use millions of colors should you the
the the first thing you should need to
know about colors is that there's only
uh like 16 default colors supported on
all Terminals and if you can get away
with using one of these um when you
change a color or something it will be
consistent with the theme if you try to
use some of the more millions of colors
approaches which we'll talk about later
those are cool and all but they they
don't comply with the theme so if
somebody changes the theme it doesn't
change that color so that's one of the
reasons just to know these basic uh
terminal colors because if you can make
your application work with that you can
be sure that the balance and the the you
know the adjustments of the C even if
it's not red or whatever it'll be it'll
be you know it'll work um if you're
getting into terminal development um you
know that's something to to to be aware
of
uh okay wait this one's white 36 is
Canan I got a hood of myself here what
is this one oh magenta 35 is
magenta magenta okay so let's go delete
this uh to delete a whole paragraph
between the blank lines dap so that's
what I'm doing
there okay so so now we've got all our
colors now wouldn't it be great if we
could randomize the color and and so um
so so then what we're going to do is is
this um we we we've got there's another
very special variable that is
automatically created for you and Bash
um called random so let's but before we
do that let's talk about what's going on
right here okay
so um this is the bash Syntax for
accessing item in the colors list array
at position or index one now most
programming languages start coding with
zero so this would be
zero uh this is zero this is one this is
two you know what I'm saying and you can
see kind of coincidentally that the
numbers 0 1 2 3 4 6 7 seven that you
know they're the same by the way if you
want bold versions of those just turn
the three into a nine add three more and
in fact let's do that I kind of want to
see if you want the if you want the
bright versions now all one of the
reasons we install westerm is because
it's got really amazing support for for
color and italics and everything not all
terminals do and it's it's you know
really well done um so yeah okay so that
made that that still doing the same
thing but it didn't it looks like it
kept it the same so if I change it to
back to six it's not a thing what if I
change it to oh wait it's not it's not
even using this because
reasons we haven't we haven't done it
yet I I apologize for that I'm getting
ahead of myself all right so um we're
still using this one so let's actually
change this one to n I'm kind of curious
nope same thing oh well I thought maybe
it would be fancier color or something
but it's not if we want to change the
color just change it to now now thinks
red is a different color oh boy that's
see that changes background
colors uh yeah I have italics now yeah
we I do have italics I I love it I
absolutely love it so um yeah we live in
you know modern times I guess wait let's
change this to 33 35 you're going to see
it's going change the color to something
else 36 I mean it thinks it's red but
obviously it's not red so anyway
wouldn't it be great if we could make it
random right so how do we make a random
that's the whole point of this so
instead of using this so this this is
printing out of color but this is
actually currently printing out the
color red but we're not able to use it
so this is where the the main part of
this comes in let's get rid of these
we'll leave
reset but how can I get it it's it's
like you can't do red I don't know what
red is but what if I wanted a random
color wouldn't it be great if there were
some way to put random color into a
variable
automatically all right there's two ways
to do this and I'm going to tell you the
only way you should ever use okay then
that is with double bra with
parentheses and everybody who knows the
back text way hold your horses we're
going to talk about it so use you always
want to use brackets here or parenthesis
so in parentheses inside here we can put
our program Rand color our our sorry our
procedure we don't need it here anymore
and now when we run it it's still red
right so it's still putting red in there
for
us and what if I change it now so so we
can change it up here let's change it to
I don't know let's change it to the
third item in the list I'm sorry the
fourth item in the list which is yellow
now let's change it to I don't know
something else now it's green so as you
can see it changes it based on the item
not not the number here which is
coincidentally is the same but you know
it changes it to that item number in the
list now here's where the randomness
comes in I want to pick a number
here That Is Random so we're going to do
that but first I want to show you this
so this here says run this and replace
it with the
output okay so that's what that does and
that that allows you to make variables
that are calling into other things and
it's extremely powerful it's one of the
best things about shell something else
to keep in mind is if I was going to
pass a string to
here you can still use double quotes in
here and you don't have to escape them
this is something a lot of veterans
don't know every
single parenthesized you know
subcommand call has its own quote
context that means that you can have
multiple things and that does not work
if you use back ticks that does not work
that only works if you use it only works
if you use parenthesis that's the same
for posic shill that that little block
of information was for the veterans are
watching um a lot of them don't know
that I didn't know for many many years
that was a thing so anyway let's
randomize this right so how do we
randomize this this number needs to be a
random number well what if we did this
random all right can we just put a
random there wouldn't that be weird if
that
worked it actually does work uh and I
want to show you in a different in a
different thing Echo random remember
everything is here Echo random Echo
random Echo random Echo random Echo
random Echo
random well true Echo we're goingon to
do this later Echo
random oops I forgot to do Echo random
sleep.
five4 I done and we get a bunch of
random numbers anybody notice a pattern
here with these random
numbers you know how many people don't
know that this exists because it has no
practical application it's just
cool this this does not have any I don't
even think this is a bash
thing um I kind of want to
know uh Echo just I want to see
something
here I I don't I
don't no oh my God what shell am I using
wait I gotta I gotta I gotta I gotta
know I got to know okay we're running
Dash now
so Dash is like super minimal
no doesn't have
it it doesn't have it it doesn't have it
so dash dash doesn't have it so not all
shells have it so my God I just killed
myself
here I just I just started raning Dash
and lock my terminal I suspended is what
I did yeah I just realized I just
suspended with
it uh well actually it's sud random yeah
this is absolutely that moment it's
really not random it's it's using the
seat on the system but kids don't care
about right so as far as you know it's
random it's not mathematically random in
other words you couldn't use it for
Bitcoin or something it's it's you know
it's predictably random um so and by the
way that's how Minecraft worlds work if
anybody doesn't know if you use the same
seed in Minecraft you always get the
same random
World pretty cool
right so yeah um anyway
and that's that gets into random Theory
which is pretty crazy so okay so Random
is already a thing but we need to pick
one of these
thing
uh yes
so it's predictively random I know but
that's I don't know what else to say so
here we go and now we're going to do a
modulus on this and I'm pretty sure it's
been a while since I've done it but I
think this is it
uh n that's not I don't want to tell you
wrong how do you do the
I do you guys know do you guys know what
the modulus operator I didn't want to
get into modulus so right
now normally if we were using this we
were doing this in Python which is what
I the way last time I taught it I taught
it in Python uh you know you just use
the random you just give you you give a
random function like the the minimum and
the maximum and you say give me a number
and you can't quite do that in in
um in in uh in in in bash so so what you
have to do is you have to use the random
function and I I honestly I forgot what
it was what's what's the module operator
and and oh no no it's percent yeah so
then we do random modulus eight so we
have eight and we want to pick one of
those
eight all right so we keep saving it
okay it's not quite enough we need to
figure this out all right so let's go
back and test it so let's say Echo
[Music]
um I think I think I might have to make
it a mathematical function yeah I do
random modulus
8 this is where this is where um this is
where bash kind of maybe not the best
beginner language but it's good as I can
do so what do we just do
there okay so let's let's actually read
about help so you can hear it from the
in the horse's mouth so to
speak
um uh wait
what that's interesting man
bash random it's not in the help text
okay each time this parameter is
referenced it expands to a random
integer we have eight though so between
zero and
32765 which I think is 2 to the
E I get that
right is it 2 the eth or 16th I don't
know most things are a factor of two or
because they're binary we're going to
get into that later I promise we're
going to make a binary counter it's
really fun um so between zero and
whatever that number is so that's that's
pretty random uh assigning it
by uh I don't know because it's binary
assigning a value to random initializes
seeds the sequence in of random
numbers oh 2 7 minus one yes because of
the unsigned type because of the sign
types yeah it's seven instead of eight I
forgot about that yeah because they
leave they always leave one off it's a
seven bit Thing versus eight bit okay
we're going to get into that we're going
to get into what a bit is and what a
bite is and how it applies and how your
computer works but not right now we're
going to get there I promise we're going
to cover that when we do the go
programming stuff because go has got one
of the best ways of seeing it ever it's
got a print up uh percent B which will
show you the binary representation of
anything that it's passed super cool the
only language that I know that has it so
uh P doesn't have that I don't think I
don't think it does even so anyway um so
what does random do so if you want to
seat
it um if you want to seat it you can do
that and your archit doesn't exist
because you're probably using Zell or
posic it's not it's a bash thing it's a
bash thing it's one another reason to
use bash so B 8 byes the 26
uh close to that smack
short yeah but we're we're talking about
something we're talking about
asky asy asky only uses seven
bit the reasons that remain unclear
actually Latin ask uses seven and the
full ask uses eight ask is I'm getting
ahead of myself
um yeah okay
so so anyway what does that do by by
doing the modu operator it says divide
it
by8 and whatever the remainder is is
what we're going to print out and if you
don't know what that means the end
effect of that is that it changes it
from being a random number between 0 and
3 32 whatever to yeah I think I thought
it was 16 that's what I thought yeah
okay because that's like a 16 million
colors thing I think that's why it was
odd it would be 36 if it were like even
okay so anyway what we're doing here so
how many of these do we have one one 2 3
four 5 six 7 8 so if you're just
starting the only thing you need to know
is you count how many of the thing you
have and you make that the number okay
and if you make that the number it will
now pick between zero
and that number so 0o and
seven okay and this is one of the
reasons that the beginning indexing
always begins at zero because the math
works out easier usually that's that's
why that's why so much stuff starts with
zero so when you start on zero you have
zero you know whatever um then uh Beyond
asky range yes which is yeah Uno which
we'll get into it's absolutely brilliant
solution that they came up with um so
here we have random 8 this says pick a
number between zero and and and it's
going to be a number between 0 and seven
inclusively if you're writing that
mathematically um this is the way to
wrot if you if you don't know in uh
interval notation let me show you this
is a math thing um so we're going to say
uh you know we could say 0 comma 7
right or we could do this we could say 0
comma 8 exclusively if you ever see this
um that's what that means did I get that
right I I I'm dyslexic a little bit so I
might have mixed it up but that's if you
ever see that in any kind of thing
that's what that
means it's because you're using version
three you're probably using version
three you need to you use ver version
five of bash yeah the version of bash
that that's on that's on Arch it's truly
veryable it's just like using really
really old version of B probably check
your version yeah so anyway this is you
know 0 to eight so what do you care so
what this means is it's going to be one
of these colors right and I did it wrong
though uh I didn't use the math notation
so we're going to do you know what I
think I think I can get away with this
nope can't do that I think I still I'm
probably going to have to do this I
didn't want to do this but I'm going to
have to do
this I think I can do that yeah there we
go there we go
so there's another thing we have to
teach you right now that I didn't want
to teach you until later that is you can
do math and specifically integer math
and this is another bism but you can do
integer math inside of Double
parentheses okay you can do integer math
inside of Double
parenthesis and so what this is doing is
it's saying calculate some number
between 1 and seven inclusively and so
every time we save it we get a new
thing right we get a new
color new color new color now the next
thing we want to do is make it so that
it keeps doing it wouldn't it be cool if
we could have it Loop so we're going to
now get
into uh
repetition and iteration and eventually
recursion but for right now we're going
to make all kinds of fun stuff right now
we're just going to repeat it so we want
to repeat this so we already know one of
them we did it already while true while
true so that means like well true is
infinite that means true is always true
do this and by the way if you want to
write it like this you can nobody does
but you can you can write it like that
if you wish oh God I forgot my sleep I
forgot my
[Laughter]
sleep stop now how do you interrupt it
everybody how do you interrupt
it how do you interrupt it no drop
frames yet how do you interrupt it
control C because that's what control C
is meant to do it's not Escape okay good
that's why I have people learn this I
forgot my
sleep let's sleep let's sleep for one
second all right now let's do it again
let's restart here we
go all right it's going to do the thing
now unfortunately now we have to like
restart it so we might as well just run
it control C is
interrupt
yes it's very weird that you don't have
that yeah all right so it's not it's not
putting a a line return which is fine
um actually let's change let's change
the uh let's change it to say
Yen then we we've written the Nan cat
disco dance party here we
go all right I have to restart it
[Music]
now all right we have to restart because
it's because it's looping right so
restart that's like way too slow we got
to speed that up we got to speed it up
let's do 0.1
seconds here we go ooh
that's kind of fun
huh there's a reason you're doing this
it's not just because you want to make
pretty things on the screen you're
learning about loops you're learning
about mathematics and Bash integer math
you're learning about how to call a
function as a variable and have its
output be the variable the variable
number interrupt regardless of the
absolutely control C sends an interrupt
on every single modern
system every single one including Bim
when you're running Bim it sends an
interrupt but bim's like eh okay well
I'll punt and make it into an escape
it's not intented it was never
intentional so it's a horrible idea I am
not going to stop saying that until
people start listening to
me mapping escape to to control C is one
of the stupidest things any human being
could ever do I dude if I interviewed
you and I knew you did that I you would
lose the interview immediately for being
so stupid I just can't
stand it telling somebody to use an
interrupt instead of escap is it's a
huge pet peeve of mine obviously okay so
there's nothing that says you're such a
noob let's make it faster how about
01 I mean it doesn't have math but it
does it oo this is much better what
about that should we do should we do a
CPU test on my computer and see how fast
it works let's see how see how fast it
is okay let's do let's let's take the
sleep
out yeah let's take the sleep
out what is going on like we have to
zoom
in oh my
lord it's a little bit too
fast zo back out it's measures in
seconds
uh so
anyway let's let's do this let's
do one tiny little niche case where it
accidentally existed and then people
still I don't understand it let's do 001
how about
that oh that's not
bad I use that's what exactly what I
use when not use keyboard control left
bracket is very difficult for Bim that's
what I use
I've been using that my whole life it
works everywhere in every B mapping that
ever exists you know what doesn't work
mapping anything else set-i will not
work look at
whatever people start picking Zell and
fish and like that that set- Obi
has been doing the whole time because
they have learned Vim wrong that's why I
get so upset because this stuff already
existed in everything that's ever been
made and because they didn't learn to
use use Escape it screwed up everything
else and so people invented this entire
ecosystem of that didn't need to
exist so I'm mad about it yeah why so
angry Boomer that's because that's the
reason people don't even know about set-
oi seriously ask the N random streamer
or YouTuber if they know what set Das V
VI does they have no idea they've never
even heard of
it anyway okay I'm going to calm down
now so
um programming apps always do stay with
the highest level of O side model so
what you are advocating strong against
mapping because mapping to an interrupt
reaches down to the Machine level just
trying to get a good handle yeah
absolutely sending an interrupt which is
designed to interrupt the
program not the action within the
program but it is allowed it sends an
interrupt signal to the
process you know trapping that
you know what you know what Bim should
have done it should have canceled the
program and exited that's what it should
have done because that's what it does in
every other thing when you do a control
C on the command line as you just saw it
interrupted the running program and
killed it that's what it usually does
and it's you can send a Sig kill instead
of a Sig interrupt a Sig kill is
unrecoverable you send a Sig kill to
anything and it automatically
dies you send a Sig interrupt and the
the application has a chance to say oh
hey hey you're trying to interrupt me I
should make a sane decision here what
should we
do and honestly Vim should have said you
did a control thing are do you are do
you want to exit VI right now that's
what it should have done because every
other program on the planet does
that but Vim decided not to do that Vim
decided that instead of it being a Sig
interrupt to thumb its nose at it and
turn it into an escape thereby ruining
an entire generation of people that's
using control C instead of Escape when
it always should have stopped and exited
vim and there would be no jokes about
how to exit VI because control C which
any rational person would have tested to
see if it could stopped the program
would have actually worked but they but
they didn't do it that way for some
reason I don't know why it should exited
the program that would have set a force
fire and you them update yeah but that's
what it should have done that's what
that's what Vim should have done you are
sending an interrupt go go do an
internet search go to an interet search
that says what is the standard thing to
do when you receive an interrupt event
go go look and at the very best the very
best you interrupt it and you trap the
interrupt and say you just sent us an
event that says you want us to stop
running you just sent us an interrupt so
do you want to interrupt your editing
session because that's the Assumption
and it would say do you want to
interrupt your session and save it cuz
that's what you just told me to
do but instead of doing that it's a
massive cluster and you know what
the fact that neovim didn't fix that in
Vim when they added it instead made it
worse it just it's just it's even it's a
to it's totally bad they could have neim
could have fixed this problem neim could
have said you know what sending a
control C should never be in Escape but
the reason they didn't is because vi
from the very dawn of time actually VI
doesn't do it it only works in Vim it
doesn't work in VI check it I don't know
why we're doing this we're not talking
about that right now we're talking about
bash but this seems keeps coming with a
thing so here I am in NBI right BL I'm
using this is this is this is you know
this is like bug for bug compatible
that's a direct quote from for for the
original bi all right now watch so I
right I'm my escapes are all working
let's do
controlc interrupted it's like okay what
got
interrupted interrup uped what got
interrupted so the only reason I can
think it would interrupt is if you maybe
did A bash thing but it didn't
interrupt right it doesn't kill it it
doesn't
escape that is temporary exit will
discard modifications yes I wanted to I
want it to just modification so so
that's what NBI does and NBI is
compatible with that if you want to get
an
Alpine uh p man run
it Alpine is not is not really bi I'm
not going to start popping up I'm afraid
I'm going to drop frames again
so I'm afraid I'm going to drop frames
again I'm not going to do it anyway back
to bash I'm sorry guys I I'm GNA
continue to harp on that and just
continue just because it's it's it's so
bad for you to learn
that we are doing bash I know somebody
got me on the tangent which isn't hard
all right
so uh you don't want to have a signal
from your terminal editor for I agree
but but you know how is that different
than Shi
ZZ it it should if you do a control C it
should send you a thing that then
prompts you and says do you really want
to exit like like Nano
does yeah anyway so so anyway don't
don't do it learn control the bracket
I'm telling you people learn control the
bracket if you have to buy an American
keyboard do it you'll you'll love it
that you did it and then you won't lose
you won't lose your VI mode all right so
here we go we got back n Cat let's go
back to our happy n
Cat there's actually uh a nine cat that
um that my uh my
friend uh somebody that I
helped wrote I'm see if I find it really
quick I think it's actually
here yeah so this is some of the things
you can do here let me show you
Ben yeah
and oh
damn there's no there's no thing
there it doesn't have it doesn't have
python
insult yeah anyway so we're going to do
one of those in another
one I looked it
up only this data and War you otherwise
what you remap ZZ horrible idea
I would never remap ZZ that would
seriously slow me down we do WQ WQ is
the same thing if you want to use WQ
that's fine I don't care it's it's
exactly the same amount of effort as C
pillz
so yeah I mean look anybody that's on a
non-american keyboard I can't help you
Vim is fundamentally broken on anything
but but an American keyboard because
it's designed for an American
keyboard all right let's let's go on
so um so we got our we got our Loop in
it's actually been an hour and we we
blew the end of our
hour talking but we did learn recru we
learned a thing we learned okay so one
last thing people let's let's before we
abandon this
permanently um let's start up our
greeter and let us let it run for a bit
while we have a conversation and we'll
wrap up this particular uh video
uh and we'll come back and then we'll
we'll talk about it but what before we
leave this video I want to talk about
what Rand color is okay what is Rand
color and the answer is it's a function
now hear me
out Rand color is a function because it
has no side effects it doesn't change
anything outside of itself and it
effectively it doesn't actually return
Bash does have return codes but they're
only integers and we'll get into zero
and one being it worked or it didn't
work um but in this case it's
functionally a function in other words
the design of Rand color is to print one
thing that you're then going to use
elsewhere and you're going to trust that
the only output from that command is
going to be a string return value of
some kind in this particular cas case
it's actually returning a binary that
you can't even see which is the which is
the ASI Escape color sequence okay so
when we get to go we're going to do go
later when we get to go you're going to
see that a function actually has a
return type a return value and
everything but for all intents and
purposes right now you can consider what
you're looking at as an actual um you
know it's it's a oops you know you can
we can consider this as as actually
being that um a function okay and if you
want to think of it this way it's it's
actually not so much a function as much
as it is an actual program and we won't
get into that right now but but the
truth of the matter is that anytime you
put two parentheses around a variable
that's got like this this is what this
does is this runs
this code in a subshell remember we
talked about processes it runs it in a
subshell it's extremely efficient
particularly bash is really efficient at
this um but what this means is is that
it it takes that command runs the
command and replaces that variable with
the output of the command that's the
takeaway the takeaway is that this runs
the command and takes it and puts it in
there so what I said earlier that these
things that we're making are kind of
like little commands inside of a bigger
command I really meant it these things
if we use them in this way which
hardcore shell people might not like
because the subshell is extra processing
power Etc but in terms of like learning
and keeping it straight in your mind it
makes it very valuable because you you
can just
say anything that happens within this
block of code this function this command
whatever you want to call it the output
of it is a thing and the fact that the
output in this case is always one thing
that there's always going to be output
and that this thing can't be used for
anything else other than you know
generating one piece of output and it
doesn't change anything outside of
itself the you know the architectural
idea is this is a function this is a
true function this is a function that
that returns something right but you
know as we'll see later if somebody were
ever to search uh well how do I you know
what are the return values of a function
the actual return value of Rand color is
in this case whatever the last command
was so you know that would be the actual
value and it would be an integer and in
this case it wouldn't be an integer so U
so that's kind of kind of a problem
right there um it returns a thing not a
code is that right yeah the the Rand
color
returns a string but the string is a
binary that is an escape sequence that
does this right now you could make like
this one okay so see the difference here
see how this says
greet so in this case greet is kind of a
procedure but it's also a function at
the same time so this is kind of a sub
routine um because it's returning it's
it's it's returning a value it's
essentially it's like printing a
string um I have a hard time with this
because in strictly speaking in shell
every single one of these things is a
procedure that has a function keyword
usually can because you can also put a
function up here this is actually one of
the reasons that shell people would
argue seriously that to don't use it as
a first language but I if the best the
best way to think of it is everything in
sub routines and they all are doing
different things um uh
yeah so uh yeah and and we haven't
gotten into conditions yet because
because we we'll get into that a bit
later so we're going to end a video
there I I'm trying to keep it from being
too confusing but hopefully this will be
be fun if you don't know about the
modular operator now you do now you know
how to do Randomness uh we got a brief
introduction to the how to do math
integer math uh and we'll do more of
that when we get into uh parameter
expansion and math and stuff like that
so the next video will be about more
things you can do that to repeat things
repetition and looping and recursion and
we're going to learn about that about
how to repeat things U we already know
while true but there's lots of other
ways to do this that's going to be next
and we're getting very close to the end
and the rest of this after that is is
kind of like you know compound
conditions and things like that and once
you have all of that you can pretty much
put together anything um so and after
that we'll do like how to write and read
from a file and we'll get into
structured data and stuff okay so uh I'm
going to take a quick break see you in a
bit